Guide to the Anderson family Papers, 1848-1963
Department of Special Collections
- Personal Letters to Helen Best Anderson.
  - Charlena van Vleck Anderson, Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson, 1912-13 (Box 33, Folder 300)
  - Charlena van Vleck Anderson, Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson, 1914-17 (Box 33, Folder 301)
  - Charlena van Vleck Anderson, Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson, 1918-23 (Box 33, Folder 302)
  - Charlena van Vleck Anderson, Letters to Malcolm Playfair Anderson, 1894-1916 (Box 33, Folder 303)
- van Vleck Family
  - Parts of Letters and undatedLetters of Balfour H. van Vleck (Box 34, Folder 304)
  - Letters of Balfour H. van Vleck to his mother Louisa van Vleck and his sister Charlena van Vleck Anderson and his brother-in-law, Melville Best Anderson 1873-1877. (Box 34, Folder 305)
  - Letters of Balfour H. van Vleck to Louisa Gurnee van Vleck, Charlena van Vleck Anderson and Melville Best Anderson, 1878-1885 (Box 34, Folder 306)
  - Letters of Balfour H. van Vleck to Louisa Gurnee van Vleck, Charlena van Vleck Anderson and Melville Best Anderson, 1886-1920 (Box 34, Folder 307)
  - Letters of Mary S. van Vleck, wife of Balfour H. Anderson, 1883-1890 (Box 34, Folder 308)
  - Letters of Mary Marvel van Vleck, second wife of Balfour H. van Vleck 1895-1926 (Box 34, Folder 309)
  - Letters of family of Balfour H. van Vleck, Mabel, Philip and Elizabeth (Box 34, Folder 310)
  - Letters of van Vleck family, summary of early letters. Pencil notes on van Vleck family by Charlena van Vleck Anderson. (Box 34, Folder 311)
  - Letters of John (Jay) Dorsey van Vleck to Louisa Gurnee, 1845-1848.Letters, Fragments, family history, notes, etc. (Box 34, Folder 312)
  - Marriage Certificate of J. Dorsey van Vleck to Louisa Gurnee, May 23, 1848 (Box 34, Folder 313)
  - Letters of J. Dorsey van Vleck to wife and children, 1862. (Box 34, Folder 314)
  - Letters of Louisa Gurnee to J. Dorsey van Vleck, 1866. (Box 34, Folder 315)
  - Letters of Dodge, Friend, to Louisa Gurnee van Vleck, 1866 (Box 34, Folder 316)
  - Letters of J. Addison van Vleck to his brother, Dorsey van Vleck, 1846-1849.S. W. van Vleck to his brother Dorsey. 1847 and 1891 (Box 34, Folder 317)
  - Letters from Harmanus van Vleck, 1848-67 (Box 34, Folder 318)
  - Letters of Amos van Vleck, son of Harmanus van Vleck, 1859 or 1860 (Box 34, Folder 319)
  - Letters of Isabel van Vleck Morgan (daughter of Harmanus van Vleck) and Winifred June Morgan (daughter of Isabel) to Charlena van Vleck Anderson. 1900 and uncertain date (Box 34, Folder 320)
  - Henry van Vleck to cousin Dorsey van Vleck Letters 1851 (Box 34, Folder 321)
  - Letters of John Harmanus van Vleck to his brother and sister 1852 (Box 34, Folder 322)
  - Letters of William Franklin van Vleck to his niece, Charlena van Vleck, 1872 (Box 34, Folder 323)
  - Letters of Nathaniel Hodskin to niece (?) Louisa Gurnee van Vleck (Box 34, Folder 324)
  - Letters of Louise Andrews to cousin Charlena van Vleck Anderson 1877 (Box 34, Folder 325)
  - Dorsey van Vleck and Louisa Gurnee van Vleck, Business papers (Box 35, Folder 326)
  - Letters of Louisa van Vleck to Charlena and Melville Best Anderson. Letters undated.Fragments (Box 35, Folder 327)
  - Letters of Louisa van Vleck to Balfour van Vleck, Charlena and Melville Best Anderson, 1872 - 1878 (Box 35, Folder 328)
  - Letters of Louisa van Vleck to Balfour van Vleck, Charlena and Melville Best Anderson. 1880 - 1885 (Box 35, Folder 329)
  - Letters of Louisa van Vleck to Charlena and Melville Best Anderson, 1886-1888 (Box 35, Folder 330)
  - Letters of Louisa van Vleck to Charlena and Melville Best Abderson and children, 1889 - 1896 (Box 35, Folder 331)
  - Letters to Louisa van Vleck from Eva Burnchweiler, 1893 - 1896 (Box 35, Folder 332)
- Miscellaneous Letters
  - Fragments (Box 36, Folder 333)
  - Doubtful relatives (Box 36, Folder 334)
  - John Anderson (Box 36, Folder 335)
  - Mabel Anderson (Box 36, Folder 336)
  - Baker (Box 36, Folder 337)
  - Bacon, Charlotte (Box 36, Folder 338)
  - Best, Carrie (Box 36, Folder 339)
  - Best, Emma and Isabel (Box 36, Folder 340)
  - Best, Harriet Cleveland (Box 36, Folder 341)
  - Best, James (Box 36, Folder 342)
  - Best, Susan (sister of Helen Best Anderson) (Box 36, Folder 343)
  - Best, Louise, (sister of Helen Best Anderson) (Box 36, Folder 344)
  - Best, William A. (Box 36, Folder 345)
  - Dobbin (Box 36, Folder 346)
  - Errington(cousin of Melville Best Anderson) (Box 36, Folder 347)
  - Hall, Henry B. and Margaret (Box 36, Folder 348)
  - Harris (Box 36, Folder 349)
  - Hooper, L. J.; Louisa; Alfred E. (Box 36, Folder 350)
  - MacDonald, Emma Morrow (Box 36, Folder 351)
  - Mather, Jessie Best, niece of Melville Best Anderson (Box 36, Folder 352)
  - Moore, Victoria (Mrs. Eli) niece of Melville Best Anderson (Box 36, Folder 353)
  - Morrow, Ermina, Sister of Helen Best Anderson (Box 36, Folder 354)
  - Oppenheim, Carrie (Niece of Helen Best Anderson) (Box 36, Folder 355)
  - Playfair, J. W.; Jane; R. P.; Robert; Margaret(Mrs. E. W. Peters (Box 36, Folder 356)
  - Potter, Arthur M. (Box 36, Folder 357)
  - Potter, Isabel P. (Mrs. C. C. Potter) (Box 36, Folder 358)
  - Schoffner, Eliza Best (Box 36, Folder 359)
  - Smith, Isabel Best (Box 36, Folder 360)
  - Sternes, Matilda (Box 36, Folder 361)
  - Vrebus, Margaret (cousin of Helen Best Anderson) (Box 36, Folder 362)
  - Letters of Byron Gurnee, brother of Louisa Gurnee van Vleck to members of the family. Some undated, 1892 - 1908 (Box 37, Folder 363)
  - Letters of Inez Gurnee, Daughter of Byron Gurnee and Mary Gurnee, to members of the Anderson Family, and Mary Gurnee. (Box 37, Folder 364)
  - Letters of M. Gurnee to his sister Louisa Gurnee van Vleck, 1862 (Box 37, Folder 365)
  - Letters of Dor Austin Gurnee (brother of Louisa Gurnee van Vleck, father of Elizabeth Gurnee who married Malcolm Playfair Anderson) to his wife Julia Leach Gurnee. Civil War Letters. And to his sister and nephew Robert. (Box 37, Folder 366)
  - Jane Gurnee Neilsen, daughter of Dor and Julia Gurnee. Emil Neilsen, Julia Gurnee, Fred Neilsen, Waldemar Neilsen. Letters (Box 37, Folder 367)
  - Letters of (Mary) Elizabeth Gurnee to Melville Best Anderson, Robert Anderson, Charlena Anderson, Malcolm Anderson, 1901 - 1912.(M. Malcolm Playfair Anderson 1915. 2. MThomas Losing 1926 (Box 37, Folder 368)
  - Letters of Edward Playfair Anderson to to father Edward Coffin Anderson and to mother Helen Best Anderson 1868 - 1879 (Box 37, Folder 369)
  - Letters of Edward Playfair Anderson to father Edward Coffin Anderson and mother Helen Best Anderson, 1880-1885and to wife Hattie Baker Anderson (Box 37, Folder 370)
  - Letters of Edward Playfair Anderson to his wife Hattie Baker Anderson, to Edward Coffin Anderson and Helen Best Anderson and to Robert van Vleck Anderson, 1886 - 1913 (Box 37, Folder 371)
  - Letters of children of Edward Playfair Playfair Anderson and Hattie Baker Anderson: Ethel, Frank and his wife Rachel, Isabel, Margaret, Dorothea A. LaFollett and Edward., (Letters of Helen in special folder) (Box 37, Folder 372)
  - Letters of Helen Best Anderson, daughter of Edward Playfair Anderson, 1902-1945 (Box 37, Folder 373)
- Letters of Edward Playfair Anderson (Box 38)
  - Letters of Edward Playfair Anderson to Melville Best Anderson 1871-1884Also fragments (Box 37, Folder 374)
  - Letters of Edward Playfair Anderson and Hattie Baker Anderson to Melville Best Anderson 1885-1888 (Box 37, Folder 375)
  - Letters of Edward Playfair Anderson and Hattie Baker Anderson to Melville Best Anderson, and to Helen Best Anderson, 1889-1890 (Box 37, Folder 376)
  - Letters of Edward Playfair Anderson and Hattie Baker Anderson to Melville Best Anderson and Helen Best Anderson, 1890-1897 (Box 37, Folder 377)
  - Letters of Edward Playfair Anderson and Hattie Baker Anderson to Melville Best Anderson, Charlena van Vleck Anderson and Robert van Vleck Anderson, 1900-1935 (Box 37, Folder 378)
- Genealogical Notes
  - Genealogical Notes, Edward Playfair Anderson (Box 39, Folder 379)
  - Genealogical Notes and Death Certificate of Charlena van Vleck Anderson (Box 39, Folder 380)
  - Genealogical Notes, Anderson Family (Box 39, Folder 381)
  - Genealogical Notes, Melville Best Anderson (Box 39, Folder 382)
  - Genealogical Notes, Gurnee Family (Box 39, Folder 383)
  - Genealogical Notes, van Vleck Family (Box 39, Folder 384)
  - Genealogical Notes, Playfair Family (Box 39, Folder 385)
  - Genealogical Notes, Best and Playfair Families (Box 39, Folder 386)
  - Genealogical Notes, Robert van Vleck Anderson (Box 39, Folder 387)
  - Genealogical Notes, Edward Coffin Anderson (Box 39, Folder 388)
- Notebooks of Malcolm Playfair Anderson
  - Early Exploring of Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 40, Folder 389)
  - Japan Korea and China, 4 volumes (Box 40, Folder 390)
    (Last vol. is 97-082)
  - China, 5 volumes (Box 40, Folder 391)
  - Catalogue of Mammals, Duke of Bedford Expedition (Box 40, Folder 392)
  - Notebooks, Peru, 3 volumes only (Box 40, Folder 393)
    5/20/97
- Expeditions of Malcolm Playfair Anderson
  - Early Discoveries of Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 394)
  - Alaskan Trip, Malcolm P. Anderson (Box 41, Folder 395)
  - Big Sur, Collection of Mammals Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 396)
  - Notes on Talks on China, Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 397)
  - West China. Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 398)
  - China Herald. Sowerby Article about Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 399)
  - China, Chao-Cheng-Shau Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 400)
  - China, Ordos Desert. Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 401)
  - Manuscript, A Tale of Western China by Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 402)
  - Manuscript, Dig Deep the Bars, A Tale of Western China, by Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 403)
  - China, Tai-Yuau-Fu, Capital of Shausi by Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 404)
  - Glen Alpine 1896Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 405)
  - Japan, Letters of a Zoological Explorer in Japan by Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 406)
  - Japan, Country Life, Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 407)
  - Japanese Puzzle, Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 408)
  - Malag (Bartons) and Alarib. Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 409)
  - Mongol Women (Dress). Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 410)
  - Mongolia, A Naturalist's Trip, Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 411)
  - Peru, Bolivia. List of Type Localities Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 412)
  - Rio Brauco. Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 413)
  - Quelpart Island, South of Korea. Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 414)
  - Siskiyou Mountains. Water Birds, List of Small Collection of Mammals. Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 41, Folder 415)
  - Publications of Malcolm Playfair Anderson: (Box 41, Folder 416)
    Birds of the Siskyou Mountains, California; A Problem in Distribution. By Malcol m Playfair Anderson and Joseph Grinnell. From the Proceedings of the Academy of Natural Sciences of Philadelphia. Jan. 1903
    Forty Days in Quelpert Island by Malcolm Playfair Anderson, Over) Overland Monthly, April 1914. Vol. LXIII, no. 4. pp 392-401.
    On Mammals Obtained by Mr. M. P. Anderson in the Philippine Islands, by Oldfield Thomas, F.R. S., F. Z. S., from the Proceedings of the Zoological Society of London, 1907. Pub. June 12, 1907
    A Winter Journey in North China by Malcolm Playfair Anderson Natural History, Vol XX, no.5, pp 516 - 531, 1920
    For the Sake of His Ancestors, by Malcolm Playfair Anderson Natural History, Vol XX no.1 pp.92 - 99, 1920.
    The Discovery of the Chinese Takin, by Malcolm Playfair Anderson. Natural History, Vol. XX no.4, 1920, pp. 428 - 433
  - Malcolm Playfair Anderson by Melville Best Anderson. The Condor, Vol. XXI, No. 3, June 1919,pp. 115 - 119. (Box 41, Folder 417)
- Photographic Prints by Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 42)
  - China (Album), Photo file (Box 58, Folder 418)
  - China, in envelopes (Box 42, Folder 419)
  - Japan, in envelopes (Box 42, Folder 420)
  - Yunan, in envelopes (Box 42, Folder 421)
  - Negative of photograph of the Empress Dowager of China (Box 42, Folder 422)
  - Catalogue of negatives (Box 42, Folder 423)
  - List of Photographs taken in China by Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 42, Folder 424)
  - Korea, in envelopes (Box 42, Folder 425)
  - Papers and clippings of interest concerning Malcolm Playfair Anderson and others, Obituary Clipping, Resumé of Career. (Box 42a, Folder 426)
  - Notes on Diaries of Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 42a, Folder 427)
  - Diploma, membership Cards, Passport (Box 42a, Folder 428)
  - Letters of Malcolm Playfair Anderson to family, 1910 - 1911 (Box 42a, Folder 429)
  - Letters of Malcolm Playfair Anderson to family, 1912 - 1913 (Box 42a, Folder 430)
  - Letters of Malcolm Playfair Anderson to family, 1914 - 1915 (Box 42a, Folder 431)
  - Letters of Malcolm Playfair Anderson to family, 1916 - 1919 (Box 42a, Folder 432)
  - Letters of Elizabeth Gurnee Anderson, (m. Ma lcolm Playfair Anderson, 1913) to Anderson Family, 1914 - 1918 (Box 42b, Folder 433)
  - Letters of Elizabeth Gurnee Anderson, (Later Lossing) to Anderson Family, 1926 - 1946 (Box 42b, Folder 434)
  - Letters of Malcolm Playfair Anderson to family, 1890 - 1896School Papers (Box 42b, Folder 435)
  - Letters of Malcolm Playfair Anderson to family, 1897 - 1901 (Box 43, Folder 436)
  - Letters of Malcolm Playfair Anderson to family, 1902 - 1905 (Box 43, Folder 437)
  - Letters of Malcolm Playfair Anderson to family, 1906 - 1908 (Box 43, Folder 438)
  - Letters of Malcolm Playfair Anderson to family, 1909 (Box 43, Folder 439)
  - Correspondence of Malcolm Playfair Anderson and Oldfield Thomas of the British Museum (Natural History) (Box 43, Folder 440)
  - Correspondence of Malcolm Playfair Anderon and Arthur deC. Sowerby. (Box 43, Folder 441)
  - General Correspondence of Malcolm Playfair Anderson (Box 43, Folder 442)
    Alphabetically Arranged.
  - Robert van Vleck Anderson, Diaries, 1893 - 1894., 3 volumes (Box 43, Folder 443)
- Diaries of Robert van Vleck Anderson
  - Robert van Vleck Anderson, Diaries 1900 - 1904., 4 volumes (Box 44, Folder 444)
  - Robert van Vleck Anderson, Diaries 1905, 5 volumes (Box 44, Folder 445)
  - Robert van Vleck Anderson, Diaries 1906, 7 volumes (Box 44, Folder 446)
  - Robert van Vleck Anderson, Diaries 1908, 1 volume (Box 44, Folder 447)
  - Robert van Vleck Anderson, Diaries 1913 - 1915, 4 volumes (Box 44, Folder 448)
  - Robert van Vleck Anderson, Diaries 1917 - 1921, 5 volumes (Box 44, Folder 449)
  - Robert van Vleck Anderson, Diaries 1922 - 1937, 9 volumes (Box 44, Folder 450)
- Publications of Robert van Vleck Anderson (Box 45)
  - Outline of a Plan to Follow in Writing a Book. (Box 45, Folder 451)
    Notes on Playfair
  - a. Earth-Flaws at the Time of the San Francisco Earthquake. (Abstract) Bulletin of the Geological Society of America. Vol. 18, 1906.By Robert van Vleck Anderson (Box 45, Folder 452)
  - b. Metamorphism by Combustion of the Hydrocarbons in the Oil Bearing Shale of California.. Reprint, Journal of Geology, Vol. XV, no. 28, 1907.By Robert va nVleck Anderson (Box 45, Folder 452)
  - c. The Great Japanese Volcano Aso. Reprint. The Popular Science Monthly. Vol. LXXI, July 1907.By Robert van Vleck Anderson. (Box 45, Folder 452)
  - d. Investigations Relating to Asphalt by Robert van Vleck Anderson and J. A. Taff, Dept. of the Interior, U. S. Geological Survey, 1908 (Box 45, Folder 452)
  - e. Petroleum and Natural Gas, by A. G. Leonard, H. E. Gregory, C. W. Washburne and Robert Anderson, Bulletin 431-A, 1909. (Box 45, Folder 452)
  - f. Account of a Trip in Southernmost Japan with Early Records of its Discovery, By Robert van Vleck Anderson. Washington, D. C. Reprint, Popular Science Monthly, Feb. 1909. (Box 45, Folder 452)
  - g. Letter, to the Editor of Science, Vol XXXVI, no. 395. 1912. (Box 45, Folder 452)
  - h. Notice. Pearson's and Standard Oil in Peru. Peru Today, Vol. V, no. 10, Jan. 1911,p. 1132. (Box 45, Folder 452)
  - a. Los Petroleos de laRepublicaa Argentina, by Robert Anderson and Emerto Longobardi, Buenos Aires, 1919 (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - b. The Selective University by Robert van Vleck Anderson. Reprint. Education, Feb. 1924. (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - c. Notes on the Earthquake and Reconstruction in Japan. By Robert Anderson. The Bulletin of the Seismological Society of America. Vol. XV, no. 2, June 1925. (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - d. Tertiary of the Punjab. Address by Robert van Vleck Anderson, Palo Alto, Jan. 30, 1926. (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - e. Tertiary Stratigraphy and Orogeny of the Punjab. Robert van Vleck Anderson. Reprint. Bulletin of the Geological Society of America. Vol. 38, Dec. 1927 (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - f. Letter to the Editor, Daily Palo Alto Times, May 24, 1929.Regarding Mooney-Billings Case. (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - g.-1 Nature's Moving Picture, by Robert vanVlock Anderson, Reprint. Science, vol. 75, no. 1944. April 1932. (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - g.-2 Pleistocene Mazouna Stage in Western algeria containing artifacts. The Bulletin of the Geological Society of america. By Robert anderson - 1932 (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - h. Letter to the Editor, The Times (London). Rejected. July 1933. (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - i. Poem Saga of Victory, Nov. 18, 1940 (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - j. Poem Ode to Eliot Blackwilder, May 1945. (Box 45, Folder 453)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1913. (Box 45, Folder 454)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1914. (Box 45, Folder 455)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1923.Accounts of Wedding of Robert van Vleck Anderson and Cracella Rountree, March 16, 1923, Obituary Notices, 1949. (Box 45, Folder 456)
  - Miscellaneous Newspaper Clippings, 1925 - 1931 (Box 45, Folder 457)
  - Who's Who in America, 1948-49.Robert van Vleck Anderson. (Box 45, Folder 458)
  - Presentation of Robert van Vleck Anderson's Geological Library to Stanford University. (Box 45, Folder 459)
  - Working Library of Dante Books and Italian Literature, used by Melville Best Anderson, presented to Stanford University by Robert van Vleck Anderson. (Box 45, Folder 460)
  - Special Papers of Robert van Vleck Anderson: Passport, Diploma, carte d'identé, Civil Service Exam. (Box 45, Folder 461)
  - War Trade Board (Box 45, Folder 462)
  - Insurance Papers, Socony Vacuum, Metropolitan, Social Security. (Box 45, Folder 463)
  - Biographical Facts and list of Publications of Robert van Vleck Anderson. (Box 45, Folder 464)
- Robert van Vleck Anderson
  - Records of Robert van Vleck Anderson and Papers of Interest. (Box 46, Folder 465)
  - Letters of Planning, Robert van Vleck Anderson. (Box 46, Folder 466)
  - Knight of the Burning Pestle, Theater Production, 1903.See Photographs. (Box 46, Folder 467)
  - Expense Accounts of Trips. 1936-1938. (Box 46, Folder 468)
  - Notes and Ideas. Rhymes. Robert van Vleck Anderson. (Box 46, Folder 469)
  - Letters of Recommendation. (Box 46, Folder 470)
  - The Shooting Star, Jan. 1897.Children's Publication. (Box 46, Folder 471)
  - Correspondence regarding Positions. 1932 (Box 46, Folder 472)
  - United States Geological Survey Grant, Correspondence, 1932. (Box 46, Folder 473)
  - Oriental Institute Correspondence, 1932(James Henry Breasted) (Box 46, Folder 474)
  - Carnegie Corporation, American Council of Learned Societies. Correspondence. (Box 46, Folder 475)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1890 - 1903 (Box 46, Folder 476)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson and assorted notes. 1902 - 1906 (Box 46, Folder 477)
  - Letters, Robert van Vleck Anderson, 1905 (Box 47, Folder 478)
  - Letters, Robert van Vleck Anderson, 1906 (Box 47, Folder 479)
  - Letters, Robert van Vleck Anderson, 1906 (Box 47, Folder 480)
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson, 1904A- General Correspondence (Box 47, Folder 481)
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson from Ralph Arnold, U. S. Geological Survey, 1906 - 1911., Special Folder (Box 47, Folder 482)
    see also #545 #554
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson from J. C. Branner, 1905 - 1912, Special Folder (Box 47, Folder 483)
    see also #546
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson General Correspondence B - J, 1905 - 1908 (Box 47, Folder 484)
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson from Roderic Crandall, Special Folder (Box 47, Folder 485)
    see also #547
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson, from David Starr Jordan, Special Folder (Box 47, Folder 486)
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson, from Kiyoshi Kawai, 1905 - 1915, Special Folder (Box 47, Folder 487)
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson from Helen and Wanda Muir, 1905 - 1909(Daughters of John Muir) (Box 47, Folder 488)
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson General Correspondence N - W, 1905 - 1906 (Box 48, Folder 489)
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson U. S. Geological Survey, 1906 - 1907, Special Folder (Box 48, Folder 490)
    also 551 567
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson General Correspondence, A - W 1908 (Box 48, Folder 491)
  - Paulsen Wireless, (Beach Thompson) 1912, (Special Folder) (Box 48, Folder 492)
  - S. Pearson and Son Correspondence, 1912, Special Folder (Box 48, Folder 493)
    also 548-50 560-64 578-79
  - Notes on Shikoku, 1905, Special Folder (Box 48, Folder 494)
  - Notes and Correspondence on Trinidad (Box 48, Folder 495)
  - Letters to Robert van Vleck Anderson from A. C. Veach, 1911 - 1912 (Box 48, Folder 496)
    568
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1907 (Box 48, Folder 497)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1907 (Box 48, Folder 498)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1908 (Box 48, Folder 499)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1908 (Box 48, Folder 500)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1909. (Box 49, Folder 501)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1910 (Box 49, Folder 502)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1911, Jan. - July. (Box 49, Folder 503)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1911, August - December (Box 49, Folder 504)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1912, Jan. - July. (Box 49, Folder 505)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1912, Aug. - Dec. (Box 49, Folder 506)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1913, Jan. - July (Box 50, Folder 507)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1913, Aug. - Dec. (Box 50, Folder 508)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1914. (Box 50, Folder 509)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1915 (Box 50, Folder 510)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1916 (Box 50, Folder 511)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1917 (Box 50, Folder 512)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1918 (Box 51, Folder 513)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1919 (Box 51, Folder 514)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1920 (Box 51, Folder 515)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1921 (Box 51, Folder 516)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family, 1922 (Box 51, Folder 517)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to Gracella Rountree, 1922 (Box 51, Folder 518)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to family and to Gracella Rountree, 1923 (Box 51, Folder 519)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to Melville Best Anderson, Charlena van Vleck Anderson and Gracella R. Anderson, 1924 (Box 52, Folder 520)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to Melville Best Anderson, Charlena van Vleck Anderson and Gracella R. Anderson, 1925 (Box 52, Folder 521)
  - Letters of Robert van Vleck Anderson to Gracella R. Anderson, 1926 (Box 52, Folder 522)